# 发财鸭
Fat Choy Duck?
# 发财呀
Fortune and Luck!
# 三叔 二伯 大爷
Uncle Wu!
# 大爷好 二伯好
- Hi, Uncle Sun! - Uncle Zheng! - Hi, guys!
# 二伯好
- Hi, Uncle Sun!
# 小焦又进来了 徒弟们好
- Xiao Jiao is here - Hello my apprentice cooks!
# 今 二伯做个什么菜啊
What does Uncle Sun plan to make today?
# 发财鸭
Fat Choy Duck
# 发财呀 发财鸭
- Fortune and Luck? - Yes, Fat Choy Duck
# 也叫发财呀
Also Fortune and Luck.
# 好 开始 来 第一步
Ok, let's get started. Step one.
# 小焦 我先处理这个鸭子 我先开火
Xiao Jiao, you can prepare the duck first while I turn on the stove.
# 这是咱们北方的白条鸭
This is Bai Tiao duck from Northern China
# 你看这鸭子选的特别好
See the duck is well chosen
# 也没有什么肥肉 关键肥肉我都去了
Doesn't have a lot of fat and I removed the rest of it
# 这个鸭子啊回来以后
After we got this duck back
# 从脊背开刀 把内脏去干净了
We start cutting from the back and remove the insides
# 然后嘴这里切了一半 师父刚教我的
Then cut the beak in half, as Shifu Sun just taught me
# 这嘴切一半啊 脑子里都入味
When you cut like this, we can marinate its head, too
# 那另一半干什么去了
Where's the other half?
# 另一半洗洗睡了 洗洗睡了
- That half? It got ready for bed - Haha, ready to sleep
# 然后我们把这鸭子先压一下
Now we put the duck in the pressure cooker
# 压一下选了几个调料去腥的
And pick a few spice to get rid of the bad flavor
# 另外几个香叶 桂皮
Then add some bay leaves, cinnamon
# 白芷 豆蔻
Baizhi (Dahurian Angelica), Cardamon
# 草果 花椒 大料小茴香
Tsao-ko, Sichuan peppercorn, star anise, and fennel seeds
# 全是增香的 对
- All add to the flavor - Right
# 但是都不多
Not a lot
# 都不多很全
But a nice combination
# 中国菜本身就是百味集中
Chinese cuisine includes hundreds of flavors in one dish
# 是永远其他菜比不了的 复合味特别强
No other cuisine can compare to its complex taste
# 大爷 你发现了没
- Uncle Zheng, did you realize? - Yes?
# 小焦说话跟他师父一样 没句号
Xiao Jiao talks just like his Shifu, none stop
# 比师傅能说 比师父能侃
- Oh, even more so - Yes, he talks even more
# 这是师父教他的· 这比师父能侃
- Shifu taught him this - Yes, he is more talkative than Shifu
# 我们是只有45分钟 好 开始了第一步
- We only have 45 minutes - Ok, here, step one
# 把这个调料先放进去
Add these spices first
# 把根留住 姜
- Keep the root first - Yes, ginger
# 刚才我师父给了我一个最好的原材料
Shifu just gave me the best ingredient
# 陈皮 特别棒 然后
- Dried mandarin peel - Superb - Yes, now
# 安然睡去 好了不脱下水吗
- Let then all go to sleep - Ok - Do we need to dry first?
# 不用 这鸭子洗干净了
No, the duck is cleaned
# 鸭子要压45分钟
Keep it in the pressure cook for 45 minutes
# 看压力
Depending on the pressure
# 现在给你加味
Now add some flavor
# 糖
Sugar
# 盐
Salt
# 因为我们这鸭子还有其他加工所以少放
Because this is the first step, don't put too much salt
# 对 有个底味就行
Yes, some basic flavor is enough
# 胡椒粉
Ground pepper
# 调料已经很多了
That was a lot of spice
# 我们给它设置了45分钟时间
And we set a 45-minute timer
# 下面你看到了没有 粗加工完了
Did you see that? We're done with pre-processing
# 徒弟做粗加工 师父做细加工
- Let's move on - Let the student does pre-processing and the teacher tweak the dish
# 这掉包了 掉包了
Oh, you're secretly changing the roles here
# 这鸭子啊
This duck
# 刚才小焦也讲了
As Xiao Jiao just said
# 压完了以后 压完了以后刚才是整张的
After the pressure cooker step, the duck, which used to be a whole
# 然后脱骨 把这骨头一蹬是吧
- Now have the bones easily removed - Yeah, remove those
# 然后这有一个模具 看到没有
Then, see this mold
# 展示展示这个模具
Show it
# 如果是家里喜欢做的话
If you don't have it when cooking at home
# 露露这个罐头 是吧 剪一下 剪圆了
The beverage can, right? Cut it to a circular shape
# 啪啪啪往上一刻 十个就出来了
Then soon you get ten of them
# 发财是金钱的意思嘛 圆嘛
Making a fortune means money, it's round, just like gold coins
# 又代表团团圆圆
Also represents family reunion
# 圆 地球也是圆的嘛
It's round, just like the earth is a sphere
# 是不是 家庭和睦也是圆的嘛
Right? Family reunion is a circle, too
# 关键过去的钱也是圆的
What really matters is that we used to use gold and silver coins
# 钱是圆的取发财之意
It's round, so what we're making today embodies wealth
# 对啊 今天用的东西就有这个
Yes, that's what we're using today
# 这个虾胶 小焦介绍一下
Xiao Jiao, can you introduce this shrimp paste?
# 小焦是玩粤菜的 玩得非常好
Xiao Jiao specializes in Cantonese cuisine, he's good
# 介绍介绍 师父也是玩粤菜的
Just so you know, Uncle Sun also makes Cantonese dishes
# 这个虾胶啊 先把它碾碎 把它整个碾碎 然后呢 剁
This shrimp paste, we first ground the whole shrimps and then mince
# 剁的不要太随 里面要有点颗粒状 这样更有口感
Don't over-mince, leave some pieces to keep the texture
# 所以我们这个已经处理好了 对 加点盐 加点味就好了
We've finished step one and we just need some salt
# 稍微加点盐 加点味就好了 这就加好了
- Yes, a little salt is enough for the flavor - Here we go
# 虾胶里面放不放猪油啊？
Should we add any lard to the shrimp paste?
# 这个虾饺里面不放猪油
We don't add lard to the shrimp paste
# 因为猪油跟这个虾啊 本身就是鲜的
Because lard and shrimp are both fresh
# 就缺少香
They only need some extra taste
# 我们给它加什么呀 加点肥膘肉
For which we can add some fatty meat
# 可以切成丁 还可以加什么呢 加冬笋丁
Cut them into little cubes, along with small chunks of bamboo shoots
# 这样把虾的鲜味和香味提取出来
To bring out the fresh and savory taste of the shrimp
# 把鸭子上边稍微放一点淀粉
Apply a little starch to the duck
# 干嘛用啊 放淀粉？
Why do we need starch?
# 要不然他们俩就分离了
Otherwise they'll fall apart
# 离婚了 咱们不能让它离婚 大过节的
They'll get a divorce. Can't let that happen on the festival
# 本来是圆满的事儿 你非让他离 你看这东西啊 不好
They ought to be happily together and now you're separating them apart, that's not great
# 你先做一件好事 让它们黏合在一起
You need to do a good deed and stick them together
# 对啊 这不就黏嘛
Yes, that's why this is sticky
# 发财鸭 发财呀
Fat Choy Duck, Fortune and Luck!
# 二伯也是左撇子啊
Oh, Uncle Sun is left-handed
# 我怎么不知道我是左撇子啊
Hey, how can I not know I'm left-handed?
# 你是左撇子啊 我一看你挤虾胶的时候是左撇子
You are though! I saw it when you prepared the shrimp
# 师父咱们做九个就得了 就也是大吉祥数字
Shifu, let's make nine, it's a perfect, auspicious number
# 小焦在这里我就放心了 我可以偷个懒
I can relax when Xiao Jiao is here. I'll take a break
# 大家注意一下啊
Attention, everyone!
# 生活需要仪式感
We need rituals in life and we need rituals for our dishes
# 菜品也需要仪式感 必须的 精加工一下 给他抹平
- Let's handle it more carefully and spread them out smoothly - Yes, spread them - With some oil
# 抹平的时候搁点油 这个不沾油就抹手上去了
Without oil, they'll all stick to my hand
# 抹完了你搁在这 弄好了
After you spread them out, leave them here
# 你看到没有 这就发财了
See this? Fortune and Luck!
# 然后你看看 这个菜 开始下一步
Now look at this, we get to the next step
# 我们可以切一半 这叫什么蛋啊 鹌鹑蛋
- We can cut them in half - What's this egg? - Quail egg
# 这个菜什么来历？ 这个菜是本人创造
- What's the origin of this dish? - I created it
# 国宴 当年这个宴会上
Years ago when I cooked for the national banquet
# 也受到特别的好评
People really liked this dish
# 就好像大牛眼是的
This looks like bull eyes
# 你没有眼睛能往前看准方向吗 能发财吗 是不是 老三？
Without eyes, can you see future directions? Can you make big money? Right, Uncle Wu?
# 今天老三表现不错啊 你看老三是善意的督促
- Today Uncle Wu performed really well - 15 minutes left - See, he's kindly reminding me
# 老大给我刨坑啊
Uncle Zheng, you're creating problems for me
# 你看 多漂亮啊
See, how pretty
# 好看吧？好看 是不是啊
- Looks good - Yes - Right?
# 跟那个牛眼似的
Like bull eyes
# 再不传就失传了
If I don't teach you all now, it'll be forgotten
# 发菜发菜
Fat Choy, Fat Choy
# 发财发财
Fortune, Fortune
# 发菜的产地在宁夏内蒙交界处
Fat Choy is produced on the border of Ningxia and Inner Mongolia
# 因为它生长的时候会破坏很多植被
Since growing it damages many other plants
# 这个产量很小
Only a small amount is produced
# 我们在做菜的时候用量也不多
We don't use much when cooking, either
# 基本上就像二伯做粤菜吧
Basically like when Uncle Sun makes Cantonese cuisine
# 粤菜里面的发菜猪手啊
There are famous Cantonese dishes like Fat Choy Pork Feet
# 发菜鸭啊
Fat Choy Duck
# 像淮扬菜做的文思豆腐啊
And the Huaiyang dish Wen Si Tofu
# 都会用到发菜 它是以点缀为主
All use Fat Choy, mostly for decoration
# 但是它也有一定的营养价值
But it also has some nutritional value
# 这有点像眼珠子的眉毛
This looks like eyebrows for eyeballs
# 现在二伯给眼珠子化妆呢
Now Uncle Sun is putting on makeup for the eye
# 这个菜你查所有的菜谱 没有
- If you look for this dish in any recipe collection - Can't find
# 查不到 对 这是独创
- Can't find - Yes, this is original
# 当年八几年的时候
In the eighties
# 我在华都做宴会的时候 经常在宴会上有一道菜
I was cooking for banquets at Huadu and often made this dish
# 他的弟子是樟茶鸭子 因为樟茶鸭好吃啊
Made based on Zhangcha duck because it's delicious
# 那时候干川菜啊 所以说这个非常受客人欢迎
Back then, cooking in Sichuan style, I found this dish very popular
# 你看那时候做川菜 现在改了 改粤菜了
See, Sichuan was popular then. Now it's Cantonese cuisine
# 二伯就是川鲁粤 样样精通
Uncle Sun cooks in Sichuan, Shandong, and Cantonese styles, good at all of them
# 我走到北京饭店上学的时候 我就仰视着北京饭店
When I went to Beijing Hotel to study, I looked up to it
# 那时候我见到郑秀生的时候 我都得这么看着
When I met Uncle Zheng Xiusheng, I had to look up to him like this
# 现在个高了 那时候他还小啊 那个时候他还没蹿个呢
Now he's tall, then he was young and he looked at me like that because he was short
# 现在长了一个大高个 现在往下看
- Haha, yes - Now you're so tall that you need to look down on me
# 那时候我见二伯也这么看 颈椎完蛋了
I used to look up to Uncle Sun like this, too. My neck hurts
# 这决策点一定要让二伯来确定
Uncle Sun needs to make the decision here
# 这个蒸出来特漂亮
It looks glorious after you steam it
# 你看你看 先搓
See, rub them first
# 你看看 你看看多漂亮
See, see, how pretty
# 另外炸的时候 油温不宜太高 （漂亮啊） 三四成就好
- Also, make sure the temperature isn't too high when you fry them - So pretty - 30% to 40% is enough
# 下油锅了
Let's start frying
# 网友朋友们
My friends
# 在家能不能直接
You can't do this directly at home
# 在家还得是笊篱
You'll need a spider
# 在这里我师父有这么多年的 有经验
Since my Shifu has years of experience
# 就不往笊篱里面放了
We don't need a spider here
# 师哥 准备装盘 你看我们的盘啊
- Shige, let's get the plate out - Yep
# 这大菜就需要仪式感啊
A great dish needs to pair with a sense of ceremony
# 盘也需要仪式感 盘在这里呢
- The plate too - It's here
# 装这里面倒下盘
- Here, flip it in the plate - Ok
# 就这温度就行啊 这颜色越浅越好
- This is the right temperature and we want the color to be as light as possible - Ok
# 得 咱们一个个捞吧
Alright, let's get them one by one
# 跟鸟巢似的
They look like bird nests
# 跟鸟巢一样
Like bird nests
# 鸟巢 行 那几个再炸上她 正合适
Bird nest? Ok, fry the rest and it's just enough
# 好了 过年的大菜 你看到没有
It's done! See? A great dish for Lunar New Year
# 你看这香气 虾的香气都出来了
See, the amazing smell of the shrimp is coming out
# 我在这里都闻见了 是吧
I can smell it from here
# 师父我觉得咱们做菜啊
Shifu, I think when we cook
# 就是任何菜啊 一个是细心加工
Like any dish, one thing is to handle them carefully
# 第二 菜一定要需要仪式感
Secondly, we really need this sense of rituals
# 而且还有什么呢 还有传承
And you know what else, cultural preservation
# 还有网友说你们做菜为什么工序这么多
Many viewers ask why we cook with so many steps
# 我说我们也想做简单的 但是实力不允许啊
I said we wanted to keep it simple, but we're just too good for that
# 那今天咱来做个仪式感的菜吧
Today we've just made something special
# 而且还有传承 还有中国过年的气氛
With traditional culture and goes along with the vibe of Lunar New Year
# 是吧 大红灯笼
Right? Lanterns, look at these big red lanterns
# 你看这大灯笼 宫灯
Palace lanterns
# 圆圆满满
Perfectly round
# 发财鸭 发财呀
Fat Choy Duck, Fortune and Luck!
# 大爷 二伯
- Uncle Zheng - Uncle Sun
# 三叔 二伯的菜出来了 出来了
- Uncle Wu - Uncle Sun finished his dish - Yes
# 您先尝尝 还是我们先尝尝啊 让小饭骨先尝
- Do you want to try first or do you want us to try? - Let our young chefs (Xiaofangu) try first
# 你每次都审人家 这回咱们被人审
Every time you critique them, now they're judging you
# 今天我们小饭骨审二伯
- Today let our young chefs critique Uncle Sun - Yes
# 发财鸭 发菜呀 吃完发财
Fat Choy Duck, Fortune and Luck! Enjoy it and make a fortune
# 吃完了发大财 发财鸭发财呀
- Eat it and earn big cash - Fat Choy Duck, Fortune and Luck
# 一口肉 一口酒 美哉
Meat with wine, amazing!
# 一口肉 一口酒 什么都有
Meat and wine, have it all!
# 2020 年什么都有
- Have it all - Have it all this upcoming 2020 - Yep
# 以下片尾部分需要复制其他视频的稿件过来